A Guide to the Militia Commission Papers, 1777-1858
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Militia Commission Papers, 1777-1858
The Library of Virginia
42222
67.71 cu. ft. (171 boxes)
Virginia. Governor's Office
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These materials most likely represent an artificial collection of records compiled from the Governor's Office Executive Papers from Patrick Henry through Henry A. Wise.
Alternative Form Available
This collection is currently in the process of being microfilmed.
Historical Information
During the colonial period of Virginia's history, the governor, as an appointee of the Crown, was the colony's principal representative and upholder of royal authority.Although his powers were limited somewhat by the Council and by the laws passed by the House of Burgesses, the governor still had the authority to prorogue, adjourn, or dissolve the legislature to confirm or veto its acts, to preside as the chief jurist of the colony, to command the provincial military forces, and to appoint many of the subordinate officers of government.
Most of these powers, excepting the military and appointive, were swept away by the American Revolution. The several revolutionary conventions assumed the executive role in 1774 and 1775 until the Committee of Safety was created in July 1775 to function in that capacity. The constitution adopted in 1776 made the governor subordinate to the legislative branch, elected by the General Assembly and circumscribed by a Council of State appointed by the assembly.
It was not until the constitution of 1851 was adopted that the power of the governor was strengthened appreciably. The Council of State was abolished and the governor was popularly elected. In subsequent years his authority was consolidated and expanded to statute, and his veto power was restored. The state government reorganization act passed by the General Assembly on April 18, 1927, firmly established the governor as the chief administrative officer of a government composed of departments, the directors of which serve at the pleasure of the governor. In addition, the organization of the governor's a staff has increased in size and complexity until it has become virtually a department itself: the Office of the Governor, encompassing both the chief executive and his staff.
Scope and Content
The Militia Commission Papers are housed in one hundred and seventy-one archival boxes and are arranged in two series. Series have been designated for Miscellaneous Records and Militia Commissions. The records include correspondence, extracts from the journals of the House of Delegates and Senate, circulars, general orders, commissions, returns, recommendations, resignations, certificates of election, and other sundry items.
Series I: Miscellaneous Records (1786-1827): This series is housed in two archival boxes and is arranged in alphabetical order. The series mostly consists of covers or endorsement pages separated from the militia commissions. In addition, there are several miscellaneous records such as correspondence from the Adjutant General's Office, brigadier general's records, cavalry and artillery records, circulars and general orders, extracts from the journals of the House of Delegates and Senate, and others.
The Adjutant General's Office Correspondence mainly contains letters from militia officers to Virginia governor and adjutant generals regarding their commissions. Noteworthy are the following documents: Governor Robert Brooke to Simon Morgan, Adjutant General, regarding the appointment of Samuel Coleman to execute the duties of adjutant general in his absence (1795 Dec. 19); the court martial papers of Major General Everard Meade (1798 Sept. 5); William Simmons, Dept. of War Accountant's Office, enclosing a copy of instructions regarding the pay and allowances of the militia while in the service of the United States (1807 Aug. 3); and Henry Dearborn, Secretary of War, acknowledging receipt of the annual return of the militia and twelve-month volunteers (1807 Dec. 8 and 1809 Feb. 11).
The Brigadier General records include correspondence to Samuel Coleman, Deputy Adjutant General, and Virginia governors regarding returns, commissions, arms, requisitions, general orders, resignations, etc. Also included are commissions, certificates of election, certificates of qualification, and resignations related to brigadier generals.
The Cavalry and Artillery records contain similar information found in the militia commission papers including commissions, correspondence, recommendations, resignations, etc., for officers in cavalry or artillery units.
The circulars and general orders originate from the governor, U. S. War Department, adjutant general, or brigadier generals between 1797 and 1813. Significant are general orders for the requisition by the President for a detachment of militia (1797 Aug. 12); a circular from Henry Dearborn, War Dept., regarding the act of 8 May 1792 providing for an annual return to be made to the President stating the military strength of each state (1802 Dec. 8); general orders for calling on the state's quota of one hundred thousand militia required by the President (1807 July 17); and general orders from Governor William H. Cabell regarding the encouragement of volunteer associations as authorized by the act of Congress on 24 February 1807 (1807 Aug. 15).
The extracts from the journals of the House of Delegates and Senate document the elections of brigadier generals between 1800 and 1811. Elections for the following brigadier generals are represented in this folder: William Nelson, Thomas White, John Smith, Hugh Holmes, James Breckinridge, William Madison, John C. Cohoon, and John Singleton. In addition, there is an extract regarding the election of Moses Green as adjutant general to supply the vacancy occasioned by the death of Simon Morgan (1811 Jan. 3).
Series II: Militia Commissions (1777-1858): This series is housed in one hundred and sixty-nine archival boxes and is arranged in three subseries. Subseries have been designated for Counties, Cities, and Resignations. Included are lists of officers, returns, recommendation, correspondence, resignations, certificates of the election of officers, and other sundry items.
Subseries A: Counties (1777-1858): Subseries A is housed in one hundred and fifty-eight archival boxes (Boxes 3-160) and is arranged in alphabetical order by county, then chronologically, with undated documents at the end of each county. The subseries mainly consists of recommendations for militia officers in the form of county court orders. There are also letters of recommendation to the governor from militia officers. In addition, there is correspondence to the governor by officers remonstrating against certain appointments. This series includes militia commissions for counties in Kentucky and West Virginia which were formerly part of Virginia.
Subseries B: Cities (1777-1858): Subseries B is housed in nine archival boxes (Boxes 161-169) and is arranged in alphabetical order by city, then chronologically, with undated documents at the end of each city. This subseries contains similar documents found in Subseries A, including court orders, letters of recommendation, certificates of election, and other documents related to the commissions of officers in the Virginia militia. Note that unknown localities are filed in Box 169 of this subseries.
Subseries C: Resignations (1823-1856): Subseries C is housed in two archival boxes (Boxes 170-171) and is arranged in chronological order. This subseries contains letters of resignation from militia officers to the adjutant general or governor between 1822 and 1856. The resignations sometimes include the commissions signed by the governor.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Miscellaneous Records
II. Militia Commissions
Militia Commissions are arranged alphabetically by county or city of origin and then chronologically within each locality.
Contents List
- Series I. Miscellaneous Records, 1786-1827., Extent: 1 cu. ft. (2 boxes). (Box 1-2)
  Series I: Miscellaneous Records (1786-1827): This series is housed in two archival boxes and is arranged in alphabetical order. The series mostly consists of covers or endorsement pages separated from the militia commissions. In addition, there are several miscellaneous records such as correspondence from the Adjutant General's Office, brigadier general's records, cavalry and artillery records, circulars and general orders, extracts from the journals of the House of Delegates and Senate, and others.
  The Adjutant General's Office Correspondence mainly contains letters from militia officers to Virginia governor and adjutant generals regarding their commissions. Noteworthy are the following documents: Governor Robert Brooke to Simon Morgan, Adjutant General, regarding the appointment of Samuel Coleman to execute the duties of adjutant general in his absence (1795 Dec. 19); the court martial papers of Major General Everard Meade (1798 Sept. 5); William Simmons, Dept. of War Accountant's Office, enclosing a copy of instructions regarding the pay and allowances of the militia while in the service of the United States (1807 Aug. 3); and Henry Dearborn, Secretary of War, acknowledging receipt of the annual return of the militia and twelve-month volunteers (1807 Dec. 8 and 1809 Feb. 11).
  The Brigadier General records include correspondence to Samuel Coleman, Deputy Adjutant General, and Virginia governors regarding returns, commissions, arms, requisitions, general orders, resignations, etc. Also included are commissions, certificates of election, certificates of qualification, and resignations related to brigadier generals.
  The Cavalry and Artillery records contain similar information found in the militia commission papers including commissions, correspondence, recommendations, resignations, etc., for officers in cavalry or artillery units.
  The circulars and general orders originate from the governor, U. S. War Department, adjutant general, or brigadier generals between 1797 and 1813. Significant are general orders for the requisition by the President for a detachment of militia (1797 Aug. 12); a circular from Henry Dearborn, War Dept., regarding the act of 8 May 1792 providing for an annual return to be made to the President stating the military strength of each state (1802 Dec. 8); general orders for calling on the state's quota of one hundred thousand militia required by the President (1807 July 17); and general orders from Governor William H. Cabell regarding the encouragement of volunteer associations as authorized by the act of Congress on 24 February 1807 (1807 Aug. 15).
  The extracts from the journals of the House of Delegates and Senate document the elections of brigadier generals between 1800 and 1811. Elections for the following brigadier generals are represented in this folder: William Nelson, Thomas White, John Smith, Hugh Holmes, James Breckinridge, William Madison, John C. Cohoon, and John Singleton. In addition, there is an extract regarding the election of Moses Green as adjutant general to supply the vacancy occasioned by the death of Simon Morgan (1811 Jan. 3).
  - Adjutant General's Office Correspondence, 1789-1809. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Applications for Quarter Master General, 1794. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1807. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1809. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1819. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1824. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1826. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1833. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1834. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1835. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1836. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1837. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1838. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1840. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1841. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1842. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1843. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1847. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1848. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1850. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1851. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Brigadier Generals, 1852. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cavalry and Artillery, 1820. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Cavalry and Artillery, 1823. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Cavalry and Artillery, 1836. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cavalry and Artillery, 1837. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Cavalry and Artillery, 1838. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Cavalry and Artillery, 1841. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Cavalry and Artillery, 1842. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Cavalry and Artillery, 1843. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Cavalry and Artillery, 1844. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Cavalry and Artillery, 1846. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Cavalry and Artillery, 1847. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Cavalry and Artillery, 1848. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Cavalry and Artillery, 1849. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Cavalry and Artillery, 1850. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Cavalry and Artillery, 1852. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Circulars and General Orders, 1797-1813. (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Covers, undated. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Extracts from Journals of the House of Delegates and Senate, 1800-1811. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Lists of Field Officers, 1793-1827. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1833-1835. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Orders for the Bedford County Militia to Rendezvous at Smithfield, 1812. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Receipt for Arms, 1810. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Requests, Deliveries, and Receipts for Articles of War, 1800-1811. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Requests for Steuben's Military Discipline, 1786-1788. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Undated. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series II. Militia Commissions, 1777-1858., Extent: 66.71 cu. ft. (169 boxes). (Box 3-171)
  Series II: Militia Commissions (1777-1858): This series is housed in one hundred and sixty-nine archival boxes and is arranged in three subseries. Subseries have been designated for Counties, Cities, and Resignations. Included are lists of officers, returns, recommendation, correspondence, resignations, certificates of the election of officers, and other sundry items.
  - Subseries A. Counties, 1777-1858.
    Subseries A is housed in one hundred and fifty-eight archival boxes (Boxes 3-160) and is arranged in alphabetical order by county, then chronologically, with undated documents at the end of each county. The subseries mainly consists of recommendations for militia officers in the form of county court orders. There are also letters of recommendation to the governor from militia officers. In addition, there is correspondence to the governor by officers remonstrating against certain appointments. This series includes militia commissions for counties in Kentucky and West Virginia which were formerly part of Virginia.
    Alphabetical by county, and then chronological within each county.
    - Accomack County, 1778. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Accomack County, 1785. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Accomack County, 1786. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Accomack County, 1789. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Accomack County, 1793. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Accomack County, 1794. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Accomack County, 1795. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Accomack County, 1796. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Accomack County, 1797. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Accomack County, 1798. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Accomack County, 1799. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Accomack County, 1800. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Accomack County, 1801. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Accomack County, 1803. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Accomack County, 1804. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Accomack County, 1805. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Accomack County, 1806. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Accomack County, 1807. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Accomack County, 1808. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Accomack County, 1809. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Accomack County, 1810. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Accomack County, 1811. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Accomack County, 1812. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Accomack County, 1813. (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Accomack County, 1814. (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Accomack County, 1815. (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Accomack County, 1816. (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Accomack County, 1817. (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Accomack County, 1818. (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Accomack County, 1819. (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Accomack County, 1820. (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Accomack County, 1821. (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Accomack County, 1822. (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Accomack County, 1823. (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Accomack County, 1824. (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Accomack County, 1825. (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Accomack County, 1826. (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Accomack County, 1827. (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Accomack County, 1828. (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Accomack County, 1829. (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Accomack County, 1830. (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Accomack County, 1831. (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Accomack County, 1832. (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Accomack County, 1833. (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Accomack County, 1834. (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Accomack County, 1835. (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Accomack County, 1836. (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Accomack County, 1837. (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Accomack County, 1838. (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Accomack County, 1839. (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Accomack County, 1840. (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Accomack County, 1841. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Accomack County, 1842. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Accomack County, 1843. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Accomack County, 1844. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Accomack County, 1845. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Accomack County, 1846. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Accomack County, 1847. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Accomack County, 1848. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Accomack County, 1849. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Accomack County, 1850. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Accomack County, 1851. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Accomack County, 1852. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Accomack County, 1853. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Accomack County, 1856. (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Accomack County, undated. (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Accomack County, undated. (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Albemarle County, 1780. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Albemarle County, 1781. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Albemarle County, 1785. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Albemarle County, 1786. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Albemarle County, 1787. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Albemarle County, 1788. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Albemarle County, 1789. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Albemarle County, 1791. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Albemarle County, 1792. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Albemarle County, 1793. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Albemarle County, 1794. (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Albemarle County, 1795. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Albemarle County, 1796. (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Albemarle County, 1797. (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Albemarle County, 1798. (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Albemarle County, 1799. (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Albemarle County, 1800. (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Albemarle County, 1801. (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Albemarle County, 1802. (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Albemarle County, 1803. (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Albemarle County, 1804. (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Albemarle County, 1805. (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Albemarle County, 1806. (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Albemarle County, 1807. (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Albemarle County, 1808. (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Albemarle County, 1809. (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Albemarle County, 1810. (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Albemarle County, 1811. (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Albemarle County, 1812. (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Albemarle County, 1813. (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Albemarle County, 1814. (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Albemarle County, 1815. (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Albemarle County, 1816. (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Albemarle County, 1817. (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Albemarle County, 1818. (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Albemarle County, 1819. (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Albemarle County, 1820. (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Albemarle County, 1821. (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Albemarle County, 1822. (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Albemarle County, 1823. (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Albemarle County, 1824. (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Albemarle County, 1825. (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Albemarle County, 1826. (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Albemarle County, 1827. (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Albemarle County, 1828. (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Albemarle County, 1829. (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Albemarle County, 1830. (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Albemarle County, 1831. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Albemarle County, 1832. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Albemarle County, 1833. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Albemarle County, 1834. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Albemarle County, 1835. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Albemarle County, 1836. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Albemarle County, 1837. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Albemarle County, 1838. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Albemarle County, 1839. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Albemarle County, 1840. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Albemarle County, 1841. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Albemarle County, 1842. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Albemarle County, 1843. (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Albemarle County, 1844. (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Albemarle County, 1845. (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Albemarle County, 1846. (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Albemarle County, 1847. (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Albemarle County, 1848. (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Albemarle County, 1849. (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Albemarle County, 1850. (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Albemarle County, 1851. (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Albemarle County, 1852. (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Albemarle County, 1853. (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Albemarle County, 1856. (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Albemarle County, undated from 1780s folders. (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Albemarle County, undated from 1790s folders. (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Albemarle County, undated from 1800s folders. (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Albemarle County, undated from 1810s folders. (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Albemarle County, undated. (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Alleghany County, 1822. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Alleghany County, 1823. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Alleghany County, 1824. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Alleghany County, 1825. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Alleghany County, 1826. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Alleghany County, 1827. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Alleghany County, 1828. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Alleghany County, 1830. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Alleghany County, 1831. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Alleghany County, 1832. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Alleghany County, 1833. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Alleghany County, 1834. (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Alleghany County, 1835. (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Alleghany County, 1836. (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Alleghany County, 1837. (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Alleghany County, 1838. (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Alleghany County, 1839. (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Alleghany County, 1840. (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Alleghany County, 1842. (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Alleghany County, 1843. (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Alleghany County, 1844. (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Alleghany County, 1845. (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Alleghany County, 1846. (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Alleghany County, 1847. (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Alleghany County, 1848. (Box 7, Folder 25)